Hey, welcome to the first actual tutorial in this series about using AutoRig Pro.
안녕하세요, AutoRig Pro 사용법을 다루는 이 시리즈의 첫 실제 튜토리얼에 오신 것을 환영합니다.
If you don't yet have AutoRig Pro, you may want to check out the first two videos.
아직 AutoRig Pro가 없다면, 앞의 두 영상을 먼저 확인해 보세요.
They are meant to help you decide if AutoRig Pro is right for you, if you should buy it.
그 영상들은 AutoRig Pro가 본인에게 맞는지, 구매해야 할지 판단하는 데 도움을 주기 위해 만든 것입니다.
If you're here, then I assume that you already have the add-on, or maybe you want to get
여기에 오셨다면 이미 애드온을 가지고 있거나, 아마도
a feel for how it works.
어떻게 작동하는지 감을 잡고 싶으실 겁니다.
In this video we'll be rigging humans.
이 영상에서는 인간형 캐릭터를 리깅해 보겠습니다.
This is one of the most common rigging tasks, and AutoRig Pro has amazing tools and automations,
이것은 가장 흔한 리깅 작업 중 하나이며, AutoRig Pro에는 훌륭한 도구와 자동화 기능이 있습니다,
but I want to emphasize that AutoRig Pro can do much more than that.
하지만 AutoRig Pro는 그보다 훨씬 많은 것을 할 수 있다는 점을 강조하고 싶습니다.
You could rig animals with it, like dogs, horses, even birds, and you can even rig fantasy creatures
개, 말, 심지어 새 같은 동물도 리깅할 수 있고, 심지어 판타지 생물들도 리깅할 수 있습니다
that don't really exist in the real world.
현실 세계에는 존재하지 않는 것들까지도요.
I think most tutorials stop at the human rig, but in this series I want to try to cover all
대부분의 튜토리얼은 인간형 리그에서 끝나지만, 이 시리즈에서는 가능한 한
sorts of scenarios that AutoRig Pro can handle.
AutoRig Pro가 처리할 수 있는 여러 가지 시나리오를 다뤄 보겠습니다.
So, if you want to see this, make sure to subscribe with notifications and so on.
그러니 이런 내용을 보고 싶다면 구독과 알림 설정 등을 꼭 해주세요.
Also feel free to let me know what kind of content you would like to see in the comments, and
또 보고 싶은 콘텐츠가 있다면 댓글로 자유롭게 알려 주세요, 그리고
I may include it in the course.
강좌에 포함할 수도 있습니다.
Okay, so next you need AutoRig Pro.
좋아요, 다음으로 AutoRig Pro가 필요합니다.
If you haven't bought it already, you can go to the add-ons page on the Blender Market
아직 구매하지 않았다면 Blender Market의 애드온 페이지로 가서
and purchase it.
구매하시면 됩니다.
I'm going to give you a link.
링크도 드리겠습니다.
It's going to be an affiliate link, which means that I'll make a little profit if you buy
제공하는 링크는 제휴 링크라서,
through it.
그걸 통해 구매하시면 제가 약간의 수익을 얻게 됩니다.
Once you've bought the add-on, you'll be able to view your order, and in here you'll
애드온을 구매하셨다면 주문 내역을 볼 수 있고, 여기에서
be able to download AutoRig Pro.
AutoRig Pro를 다운로드할 수 있습니다.
And below it, you'll see a README on how to install the add-ons.
그리고 그 아래에는 애드온 설치 방법에 대한 README가 있습니다.
So download these files, and you can go ahead and read the text file, or you can keep watching
그러니 파일들을 다운로드하시고, 텍스트 파일을 읽으셔도 되고, 아니면 계속해서
the video.
이 영상을 보셔도 됩니다.
I'm going to show you how to install the add-on.
애드온 설치 방법을 보여드리겠습니다.
So usually, when you download an add-on as a zip file, you can just go to Edit, Preferences,
보통 애드온을 ZIP 파일로 다운로드했으면, Edit > Preferences로 이동해서
Add-ons, click Install, and go ahead and install the zip file that you downloaded.
Add-ons에서 Install을 눌러 다운로드한 ZIP 파일을 설치하면 됩니다.
In the case of AutoRig Pro, it is a little bit different.
하지만 AutoRig Pro는 약간 다릅니다.
Here I'm going to open up the zip file.
여기서는 ZIP 파일을 열어보겠습니다.
Here is the contents, and you'll see that it contains a .py file, and two more zip files,
내용물을 보면 .py 파일 하나와 ZIP 파일 두 개,
and a 2.79 folder.
그리고 2.79 폴더가 들어 있습니다.
You have to unzip these files somewhere on your hard drive.
이 파일들을 하드 드라이브 어딘가에 압축 해제해 두어야 합니다.
So personally, I have a special folder where I place the newest version of AutoRig Pro.
개인적으로 저는 AutoRig Pro 최신 버전을 넣어두는 전용 폴더를 사용합니다.
So here I'm going to delete the previous version that I had, and just select all of these files
그래서 여기서는 이전 버전을 삭제하고, 이 파일들을 모두 선택해서
and place them in this folder.
이 폴더에 넣겠습니다.
If you're using the ancient Blender 2.79, then go into this folder, and you can use these
아주 오래된 Blender 2.79를 사용 중이라면 이 폴더로 가서,
special files for the older Blender version.
이 구버전용 특수 파일들을 사용하시면 됩니다.
I've never done that, and I'm not going to cover this.
저는 그렇게 해본 적이 없고, 여기서는 다루지 않겠습니다.
Personally I'll be using the newest version of Blender, Blender 3.2, and the newest version
저는 최신 버전의 Blender, 즉 Blender 3.2와
of AutoRig Pro.
최신 버전의 AutoRig Pro를 사용할 것입니다.
So the actual AutoRig Pro add-on is this one, AutoRig Pro Master.zip.
실제 AutoRig Pro 애드온은 이 AutoRig Pro Master.zip입니다.
The Proxy Picker is an additional tool that I'll cover in a separate video, and RigTools.zip
Proxy Picker는 별도의 영상에서 다룰 추가 도구이고, RigTools.zip은
is a mini add-on that you can send to someone else when you're sharing your AutoRig Pro rig
AutoRig Pro 리그를 공유할 때 상대에게 보낼 수 있는 미니 애드온입니다.
with them.
상대방에게 함께 보내는 용도입니다.
To make full use of the rig, they need this mini add-on, and it's very important that
리그를 온전히 사용하려면 이 미니 애드온이 필요하고, 또한 매우 중요한 점은
you do not install both add-ons.
두 애드온을 동시에 설치하면 안 된다는 것입니다.
So in this case, we are only going to install AutoRig Pro Master, okay?
그래서 여기서는 AutoRig Pro Master만 설치하겠습니다, 알겠죠?
I'll go back to Blender, Edit, Preferences, Add-ons, click on Install, and I'll go to my
Blender로 돌아가서 Edit > Preferences > Add-ons로 가서 Install을 클릭하고,
folder where I keep AutoRig Pro, and highlight AutoRig Pro Master and install it.
AutoRig Pro를 보관하는 폴더에서 AutoRig Pro Master를 선택해 설치하겠습니다.
And then I'll put a check mark next to the add-on's name.
그리고 애드온 이름 옆에 체크 표시를 하겠습니다.
There are some add-ons options that I'm going to cover in another video.
애드온 옵션 몇 가지는 다른 영상에서 다루겠습니다.
In this video, I just want to keep it simple and focus on some of the most useful and commonly
이번 영상에서는 단순하게 유지하고, 가장 유용하고 자주
used features.
사용되는 기능에 집중하겠습니다.
So in this video, I'm going to show you two examples of rigging a humanoid character.
그래서 이번 영상에서는 인간형 캐릭터를 리깅하는 두 가지 예제를 보여드리겠습니다.
One will be very simple, and the other one will be more complex.
하나는 아주 단순하고, 다른 하나는 좀 더 복잡합니다.
It is only because AutoRig Pro has really cool features that I can use such a complex character
AutoRig Pro에 정말 멋진 기능들이 있기 때문에, 이렇게 복잡한 캐릭터를
in a beginner's tutorial.
초급자용 튜토리얼에서도 사용할 수 있는 것입니다.
And if you want to follow along with me with the exact models that I'm using, I'm going
그리고 제가 사용하는 바로 그 모델들로 함께 따라 하고 싶다면, 저는
to share these models for free on Gumroad.
이 모델들을 Gumroad에서 무료로 공유할 예정입니다.
And most likely, you'll be able to pay a little extra and get some bonuses, but you'll be able
또 아마 소액을 추가로 지불해 보너스를 얻을 수도 있겠지만, 기본 파일들은
to get the main files for free.
무료로 받으실 수 있을 겁니다.
I'll share a link to the Gumroad page in the video notes.
영상 설명에 Gumroad 페이지 링크를 공유하겠습니다.
Okay, so I'll open my first file, and it should be called something like ARP Rigging Simple.
좋습니다. 먼저 첫 번째 파일을 열겠는데, 이름은 'ARP Rigging Simple' 같은 것일 겁니다.
And when you open it, you should see this file here.
열어보면 이렇게 이 파일이 보일 겁니다.
You may recognize this guy from my Rigify series.
이 친구는 제 Rigify 시리즈에서 본 적이 있을 겁니다.
And up here, you'll see a little info about the license.
그리고 위쪽에는 라이선스에 대한 간단한 안내가 있습니다.
Basically, this is my file.
기본적으로, 이건 제 파일입니다.
I'm releasing it as Creative Commons, so you can use it for whatever you like.
저는 이 파일을 크리에이티브 커먼즈로 배포하니, 원하는 용도로 사용하셔도 됩니다.
Just try to credit CGDive, and thank you if you do.
다만 'CGDive' 출처 표기를 부탁드리고, 표기해 주시면 감사합니다.
And then I'm going to close this and focus on my character.
그다음 이 창은 닫고 캐릭터 작업에 집중하겠습니다.
So I just installed AutoRig Pro.
방금 AutoRig Pro를 설치했습니다.
So if I open the end panel here, I'll have the ARP ARP tab.
여기 N 패널을 열면 ARP ARP 탭이 보일 겁니다.
And here is the main AutoRig Pro interface.
여기가 AutoRig Pro의 주요 인터페이스입니다.
At the top, you'll have the AutoRig Pro rigging features.
상단에는 AutoRig Pro 리깅 기능이 있고,
Below it is the smart features, which we'll actually be using in a second.
그 아래에는 'Smart' 기능이 있으며, 곧바로 이걸 사용할 겁니다.
The smart features allow you to rig a humanoid character really simply.
Smart 기능은 인간형 캐릭터를 아주 간단하게 리깅할 수 있게 해줍니다.
Remap is actually retargeting.
'Remap'은 사실 리타게팅 기능입니다.
And I already covered retargeting.
리타게팅은 이미 다룬 바 있습니다.
If you want to know how to use this feature in AutoRig Pro, I already have a really in-depth
AutoRig Pro에서 이 기능을 사용하는 법을 알고 싶다면, 아주 자세하게 설명한
video about that.
영상이 이미 있습니다.
And I'll share a link.
그리고 링크를 공유하겠습니다.
And finally, we have export, which basically helps you export AutoRig Pro rigs to game
마지막으로 'Export'가 있는데, 기본적으로 AutoRig Pro 리그를 게임 엔진이나
engines or other applications.
다른 애플리케이션으로 내보내는 데 도움을 줍니다.
But mainly game engines, and there are special presets for Unity and Unreal.
주로 게임 엔진이며, Unity와 Unreal을 위한 특별한 프리셋이 있습니다.
Alright, that was the overview.
좋습니다, 개요는 여기까지입니다.
Now we're going to focus on the smart features.
이제 Smart 기능에 집중해 보겠습니다.
So I'm going to select my little character here, click the only button that I see here
여기 작은 캐릭터를 선택하고, Smart 아래 보이는 유일한 버튼인
under smart, get selected objects.
'Get Selected Objects'를 클릭하겠습니다.
You have the choice between full body and facial only.
'Full Body'와 'Facial Only' 중에서 선택할 수 있습니다.
We're going to be doing the body now, so full body and press OK.
지금은 바디 작업이므로 'Full Body'를 선택하고 OK를 누릅니다.
When we press OK, AutoRig Pro automatically puts us in front view, and it gives us these buttons.
OK를 누르면 AutoRig Pro가 자동으로 정면 보기로 전환하고, 이런 버튼들을 보여줍니다.
So the main button that we are interested in is this Add button.
우리가 주목할 주된 버튼은 이 'Add' 버튼입니다.
So first we want to add the neck.
먼저 목을 추가합니다.
When I press the button, this circle will appear, and I can place it somewhere at the base of the neck.
버튼을 누르면 이런 원이 나타나고, 목의 기저부 쪽 어딘가에 배치할 수 있습니다.
There isn't a very precise guide as to where to place these points, but you don't have to be super precise.
이 포인트들을 정확히 어디에 놓아야 하는지에 대한 엄밀한 기준은 없지만, 아주 정확할 필요는 없습니다.
And you can also fine-tune the placement of the actual bones later.
그리고 실제 뼈의 위치는 나중에 미세 조정할 수도 있습니다.
You'll see that in a minute.
곧 확인해 보겠습니다.
So next I want to place a chin.
다음으로 턱을 배치하겠습니다.
So I'm going to place it around here, and I can also zoom in.
여기쯤에 놓고, 확대도 할 수 있습니다.
Once I've clicked to confirm, I can always press G again and keep moving the marker.
클릭해 확정한 뒤에도 G를 눌러 계속 마커를 옮길 수 있습니다.
Next, I'm going to zoom out and add the shoulders.
다음으로 축소해서 어깨를 추가하겠습니다.
So when placing the shoulders, don't really place them on the top of the shoulder.
어깨를 배치할 때는, 어깨의 맨 위에 올려놓지 마세요.
Place it a little bit inside the volume of the shoulder.
어깨 볼륨의 약간 안쪽에 배치합니다.
Something like this.
이런 느낌으로요.
And if your character is symmetrical like mine, you can keep the mirror option on,
제 캐릭터처럼 대칭이라면 'Mirror' 옵션을 켠 채로
and you can simply work on one marker and the other one will be set up automatically.
한쪽만 작업해도 다른 쪽이 자동으로 설정됩니다.
If your character is not symmetrical, then you can turn off mirror and move each one individually.
대칭이 아니라면 'Mirror'를 끄고 각각 따로 옮기면 됩니다.
But in my case, I want to use the mirror option to save some time.
하지만 제 경우에는 시간을 아끼기 위해 Mirror 옵션을 사용하겠습니다.
So next we want to add the wrist, like this.
다음으로 손목을 이렇게 추가합니다.
Next, spine root.
다음은 Spine Root입니다.
So again, this is not entirely clear, but place it somewhere in the crotch area,
여기도 명확한 기준은 없지만, 사타구니 부근 어딘가에
maybe a little bit higher, something like this, where the base of the spine would be.
척추가 시작되는 지점 정도, 약간 위쪽에 이런 식으로 두면 됩니다.
And next we want to add the ankles.
그리고 발목을 추가합니다.
So somewhere here.
이쯤에요.
And here is another important tip.
여기서 또 하나 중요한 팁이 있습니다.
You only need to place these markers from the front view.
이 마커들은 정면 보기에서만 배치하면 됩니다.
Technically, you can go to the side view.
기술적으로는 측면 보기로 가도 됩니다.
In this case, they are already kind of in a good position,
이 경우에는 이미 꽤 괜찮은 위치에 있지만,
but you can possibly try to move them around, but you don't need to.
움직여 보아도 되지만, 그럴 필요는 없습니다.
You just need to place them from the front view and then Autoric Pro knows what to do.
정면에서만 배치하면 AutoRig Pro가 나머지는 알아서 처리합니다.
One exception may be the ankle.
예외가 될 수 있는 것은 발목입니다.
I just find it a little bit easier to find the right spot from the side view.
측면 보기에서 알맞은 위치를 찾기가 조금 더 쉬운 것 같습니다.
So something like this.
이런 식으로요.
These are all of the markers that we need.
이것들이 우리가 필요한 모든 마커입니다.
Next, Autoric Pro will try to automatically place all of the bones, including fingers.
다음으로 AutoRig Pro가 손가락을 포함한 모든 뼈를 자동으로 배치하려고 합니다.
And it will try to detect the fingers automatically.
손가락도 자동으로 감지하려고 시도합니다.
We just need to let it know how many fingers there are.
우리는 손가락이 몇 개인지만 알려주면 됩니다.
You can have up to five, like in a realistic human.
사람처럼 최대 다섯 개까지 설정할 수 있습니다.
But in this case, my character is simplified and it has basically a glove hand.
하지만 이 경우 제 캐릭터는 단순화되어 있어서 사실상 장갑 같은 손을 갖고 있습니다.
So basically I have two fingers.
그래서 기본적으로 손가락이 두 개라고 보면 됩니다.
This big lump and then the thumb.
큰 하나의 덩어리와 엄지손가락이요.
So I'm going to set my number of fingers to two.
그래서 손가락 수를 2로 설정하겠습니다.
Below it are the settings for the automatic finger detection.
그 아래에는 자동 손가락 감지 설정이 있습니다.
I usually just use the default settings and it tends to work well.
보통 기본값만 사용해도 잘 작동합니다.
And if it doesn't, then we can tweak the fingers manually.
만약 잘 안 되면 손가락을 수동으로 조정하면 됩니다.
I'm going to show you this as well.
이 부분도 보여드리겠습니다.
Most of the settings we're going to leave to default.
대부분의 설정은 기본값으로 두겠습니다.
So this skeleton setting is mainly if you're going to be using Unreal.
이 'Skeleton' 설정은 주로 언리얼을 사용할 때를 위한 것입니다.
For now, we're going to leave it to default.
지금은 기본값으로 두겠습니다.
Spine count will define how many spine bones there will be.
'Spine Count'는 척추 뼈의 개수를 정합니다.
My character is kind of simple, so three is fine.
제 캐릭터는 꽤 단순하니 3이면 충분합니다.
These next options are kind of advanced.
다소 고급 기능입니다.
We can talk about them in another video.
이 부분은 다른 영상에서 다루겠습니다.
Neck count will define how many neck bones there will be.
'Neck Count'는 목 뼈의 개수입니다.
This character again is kind of simple.
이 캐릭터도 역시 단순합니다.
One is fine.
하나면 충분합니다.
Twist count is the number of twist bones.
'Twist Count'는 트위스트 뼈의 개수입니다.
So in the legs and arms, each part of the limb.
팔과 다리, 각 사지의 구간에 대해요.
So for example, the upper arm and the lower arm can have twist bones.
예를 들어 상완과 하완에 트위스트 뼈를 둘 수 있습니다.
And they should have twist bones because that helps with the deformation.
그리고 변형 품질에 도움이 되므로 트위스트 뼈를 두는 것이 좋습니다.
Of the character.
캐릭터의 변형이요.
So the default is twist count of one.
기본값은 트위스트 개수 1입니다.
Which means that one additional bone will be placed here at the shoulder.
즉 어깨 쪽에 추가 뼈가 하나 배치된다는 뜻이고,
And one at the wrist.
손목에도 하나 배치됩니다.
And that will help improve the deformations.
이것이 변형 품질을 향상시키는 데 도움이 됩니다.
And it is similar with the leg.
다리도 마찬가지입니다.
So I'm going to keep this to default.
그래서 이 설정은 기본값으로 두겠습니다.
Then we have facial setup.
다음은 얼굴 세팅입니다.
And my character doesn't have any face features.
제 캐릭터에는 얼굴 디테일이 없습니다.
So I'm going to skip this.
그래서 이 부분은 건너뛰겠습니다.
And I can go ahead and press go.
그러면 'Go'를 눌러 진행하겠습니다.
Which will create some bones for me.
그러면 몇 가지 뼈가 생성됩니다.
So it is important to understand that this is not the final rig.
여기서 중요한 점은, 이것이 최종 리그가 아니라는 것입니다.
These are the so-called reference bones.
이것들은 일명 '레퍼런스 본'입니다.
Or if you have Rigify experience, you can call it MetaRig.
Rigify를 써본 분이라면 '메타리그'라고 부를 수도 있죠.
So in most cases, ARP will do a good job at placing the bones at the right places.
대부분의 경우 ARP가 뼈를 적절한 위치에 잘 배치해 줍니다.
Usually, the elbow may need a little bit of tweaking.
보통 팔꿈치 쪽은 약간의 조정이 필요할 수 있습니다.
For the elbow, it is important, just like in Rigify, that the arm is not too straight.
Rigify와 마찬가지로 팔꿈치에서는 팔이 너무 일직선이 되지 않도록 하는 것이 중요합니다.
You want to give a little bit of an angle to these two bones.
이 두 뼈에 약간의 각도를 주어야 합니다.
Autoreg Pro will do this automatically.
AutoRig Pro가 자동으로 그렇게 해주기도 합니다.
But if you're tweaking this position, then keep that in mind.
하지만 직접 위치를 조정한다면 이 점을 명심하세요.
And here we can see the placement of the fingers.
여기에서는 손가락 배치를 확인할 수 있습니다.
It is not bad, but we can tweak it a little bit.
나쁘지 않지만 약간 손보면 더 좋습니다.
If I look from the front view, this joint here seems a little bit misplaced.
정면에서 보면, 이 관절이 약간 잘못 놓인 것처럼 보입니다.
I'm just going to move it deeper inside the hand.
손 안쪽으로 더 깊게 옮기겠습니다.
So something like this.
이런 식으로요.
And then this joint can be a little bit deeper into the thump.
그리고 이 관절은 엄지 쪽으로 조금 더 안쪽에 두면 됩니다.
Okay, this looks good.
좋아요, 괜찮아 보입니다.
The knee can be a little bit lower.
무릎은 약간 더 아래로 내려도 됩니다.
And these bones, these little bones at the foot, will determine the behavior of the foot.
그리고 이 작은 발 뼈들은 발의 동작 방식을 결정합니다.
And we kind of need to place them at the edges of the foot.
발의 가장자리 부근에 배치해 주어야 합니다.
Something like this.
이런 식으로요.
When working with the reference bones, you can go to the Autoreg Pro tab.
레퍼런스 본으로 작업할 때는 AutoRig Pro 탭으로 이동할 수 있습니다.
And in here, you have a bunch of useful features, which I'm going to cover in an advanced video.
여기에 유용한 기능들이 많이 있는데, 이들은 고급편에서 다루겠습니다.
For now, I just want to show you how easy it is to achieve good results with just the default settings.
지금은 기본 설정만으로도 좋은 결과를 얼마나 쉽게 얻을 수 있는지 보여드리려 합니다.
But basically, if you select any of these bones, you have limp options for each of the parts of the rig.
기본적으로, 이 뼈들 중 하나를 선택하면 리그 각 부분에 대한 여러 옵션을 사용할 수 있습니다.
You can duplicate them and delete them and so on to create advanced rigs.
복제하거나 삭제하는 등으로 더 고급 리그를 만들 수 있습니다.
But for now, I just want to go ahead and click match to rig.
하지만 지금은 'Match to Rig'를 클릭하겠습니다.
So this is the magic button that will create an advanced rig for you.
이 버튼이 여러분을 위해 고급 리그를 만들어 주는 마법 같은 버튼입니다.
So let's click it.
그럼 클릭해 보겠습니다.
And you'll see these pretty shapes that Autoreg Pro created for us.
AutoRig Pro가 만들어 준 예쁜 컨트롤 형태들이 보일 겁니다.
And that's it. The rig is actually working.
이게 전부입니다. 리그가 실제로 작동합니다.
We can go to pause mode now and give it a try.
이제 포즈 모드로 전환해 테스트해 보겠습니다.
So you'll see that something is happening, but the character itself is not moving.
뭔가가 움직이는 건 보이지만, 정작 캐릭터 자체는 움직이지 않습니다.
To make sure that our rig moves the character, there is a process called binding or skinning or weighting.
리그가 캐릭터를 움직이게 하려면 바인딩(스키닝/웨이팅)이라고 하는 과정이 필요합니다.
So I'll go to object mode and click on the skin tab under Autoreg Pro.
그래서 오브젝트 모드로 가서 AutoRig Pro의 Skin 탭을 클릭하겠습니다.
I'm going to select the mesh and then shift select the character.
메시를 선택한 다음 캐릭터를 Shift로 추가 선택합니다.
And Autoreg Pro has a bunch of advanced binding options.
그리고 AutoRig Pro에는 다양한 고급 바인딩 옵션이 있습니다.
And I'm actually going to cover some of them in the next example in the advanced character.
이 중 일부는 다음 예제, 고급 캐릭터에서 다루겠습니다.
But for this simple character, you can just press the bind button.
하지만 이 단순한 캐릭터의 경우에는 'Bind' 버튼만 누르면 됩니다.
And a second later, you can go to your rig, go to pause mode.
잠시 뒤 리그로 가서 포즈 모드로 전환합니다.
By the way, I'm using a pie menu. You can just go in here and choose pause mode.
참고로 저는 파이 메뉴를 사용하고 있습니다. 여기에서 포즈 모드를 선택해도 됩니다.
And now if you move the hand, for example, the whole arm will be moving in IK mode.
이제 예를 들어 손을 움직이면, 전체 팔이 IK 모드로 움직입니다.
I'm going to try to give you an overview of the rig controls.
리그 컨트롤을 간단히 개관해 보겠습니다.
For now, let's not go too deep into this.
지금은 너무 깊게 들어가진 않겠습니다.
But you can see that the character is moving with the rig and you can see how easy it was.
하지만 캐릭터가 리그와 함께 움직이는 것을 보셨고, 얼마나 쉬웠는지도 알 수 있습니다.
We just placed a couple of markers, pressed a couple of buttons and now we have this.
몇 개의 마커를 배치하고 버튼 몇 번 눌렀을 뿐인데, 이제 이렇게 됐습니다.
We have a moving character. It's pretty cool.
움직이는 캐릭터를 얻었죠. 꽤 멋집니다.
So I hope this shows you that rigging, especially when using an Autorigger, doesn't need to be scary.
특히 오토리거를 사용할 때 리깅이 전혀 두려울 필요가 없다는 것을 보여드렸길 바랍니다.
And when you're ready, let's move on to the advanced example.
준비가 되셨다면 이제 고급 예제로 넘어가겠습니다.
I'm going to open my complex human example.
복잡한 인간형 예제를 열겠습니다.
Here it is.
바로 이겁니다.
And again, here you can read the license.
여기에서도 라이선스를 확인하실 수 있습니다.
In this case, I downloaded this model from Sketchfab.
이 모델은 Sketchfab에서 다운로드했습니다.
The license was Creative Commons Attribution, which means that I have to give credit to the original creator.
라이선스는 CC BY여서 원작자 표기를 해야 합니다.
Thank you for this great model.
멋진 모델을 제공해 주셔서 감사합니다.
And I did some edits myself.
그리고 저도 몇 가지 수정을 했습니다.
Basically, when you import Sketchfab models into Blender, they can have some problems and I just cleaned up the model and the materials.
기본적으로 Sketchfab 모델을 Blender로 가져오면 문제가 있을 수 있어서, 모델과 머티리얼을 정리했습니다.
So again, feel free to use this model for any purpose, as long as you credit the creators.
그러니 창작자들을 표기하는 조건으로, 이 모델은 자유롭게 사용하셔도 됩니다.
So let's take a quick look at this model.
이 모델을 간단히 살펴보겠습니다.
It actually consists of several separate meshes.
실제로 여러 개의 분리된 메시로 구성되어 있습니다.
So the main one is this body mesh, which I can hide.
주요 메시가 이 바디 메시로, 이렇게 숨길 수 있습니다.
And then there is a hair mesh.
그리고 헤어 메시가 있고,
Both eyes are a separate object.
두 눈도 별도의 오브젝트입니다.
There are eyelashes, upper teeth, lower teeth and a tongue.
속눈썹, 윗니, 아랫니, 그리고 혀도 있습니다.
So let's undo.
되돌리겠습니다.
And Alt H to unhide everything.
그리고 Alt+H로 전부 다시 보이게 하겠습니다.
So if you have a similar model, but everything is joined into a single object, I can do something like this.
비슷한 모델인데 모든 것이 하나의 오브젝트로 합쳐져 있다면, 이렇게 할 수 있습니다.
Just select everything, Ctrl J and join.
모두 선택한 다음 Ctrl+J로 합치세요.
And then I could go to edit mode and press L to select the different parts that I want to separate into a separate object.
그런 다음 편집 모드로 들어가서, 분리하고 싶은 부분 위에서 L을 눌러 해당 부분을 선택합니다.
I can also box select like this and then press Ctrl L and that will complete the selection.
이렇게 박스 선택을 한 뒤 Ctrl+L을 눌러 연결된 모든 요소를 선택할 수도 있습니다.
And now, let's see.
이제, 한번 보죠.
Another technique is to enable X-Ray.
또 다른 방법은 X-Ray를 켜는 것입니다.
Okay.
좋습니다.
And now everything that I wanted is selected.
이제 원하는 것들이 모두 선택되었습니다.
I'm going to press P and split it into a new model.
P를 눌러 새 오브젝트로 분리하겠습니다.
And I can keep doing this, just selecting the meshes and separating them.
이런 식으로 메시를 선택해서 계속 분리해 나갈 수 있습니다.
So I'm going to just undo.
여기서는 되돌리겠습니다.
And get my separate meshes.
그리고 분리된 메시들을 그대로 사용하겠습니다.
And when rigging this kind of complex character with AutoRig Pro, you may want to hide meshes that will get in the way.
이런 복잡한 캐릭터를 AutoRig Pro로 리깅할 때는, 방해가 되는 메시를 숨기는 것이 좋습니다.
Especially when doing the facial setup.
특히 얼굴 세팅을 할 때요.
This character has facial features.
이 캐릭터는 얼굴 디테일이 있습니다.
So we are going to rig the face as well.
그래서 얼굴도 함께 리깅하겠습니다.
So I want to hide the hair and also the eyelashes.
그래서 헤어와 속눈썹을 숨기겠습니다.
I'll explain why in a second.
이유는 곧 설명드리죠.
Okay, so with that, I can just box select over the whole character.
좋습니다. 이렇게 해서 캐릭터 전체를 박스 선택하면,
This will also select the teeth.
이때 치아도 함께 선택됩니다.
That is not that important because they are inside.
하지만 치아는 내부에 있으니 크게 중요하지 않습니다.
So they won't get in the way.
그래서 방해가 되진 않을 겁니다.
So then I can go to ARP, Smart.
그런 다음 ARP의 Smart로 갑니다.
And I have to make one of the objects active.
오브젝트 중 하나를 활성 상태로 만들어야 합니다.
So just shift and click on it.
Shift를 누른 채 클릭하면 됩니다.
Go to Smart and get selected objects.
Smart에서 'Get Selected Objects'를 실행합니다.
Choose full body and press OK.
'Full Body'를 선택하고 OK를 누릅니다.
So now the process is the same as in the previous part.
이제 절차는 앞부분과 동일합니다.
Add neck.
목을 추가합니다.
Add chin.
턱을 추가합니다.
Add shoulders.
어깨를 추가합니다.
Kind of inside the shoulder volume.
어깨 볼륨 안쪽에 배치합니다.
Add wrists.
손목을 추가합니다.
Add spine root.
Spine Root를 추가합니다.
Add ankles.
발목을 추가합니다.
Again, I'm going to look from the side view just for the ankles.
발목만은 다시 측면에서 보겠습니다.
And place them around here.
이쯤에 배치합니다.
Now this is a realistic character and it has five fingers.
이건 사실적인 캐릭터라 손가락이 다섯 개입니다.
So number of fingers, five.
그래서 손가락 수는 5개입니다.
And the detection settings, I'll just leave to default.
감지 설정은 기본값으로 두겠습니다.
Spine count and the other settings, I'll leave to default.
Spine Count와 다른 설정들도 기본값으로 두겠습니다.
And then I want to do the facial setup.
그다음 얼굴 세팅을 하겠습니다.
Just press on the button and go to front view.
버튼을 누르고 정면 보기로 가세요.
And Autoreg Pro gives us these lines that we want to align to our character.
AutoRig Pro가 이런 선들을 제공하는데, 캐릭터에 맞춰 정렬하면 됩니다.
So first there is the chin.
먼저 턱입니다.
And just like with the body markers, there is no precise guide as to where to place them.
바디 마커와 마찬가지로 정확한 위치 기준은 없습니다.
But a lot of them actually make sense.
하지만 대부분은 보면 감이 옵니다.
So for example, this is the chin line.
예를 들어 이것이 턱 라인이고,
So I want to place the lower dot at the bottom of the chin and the upper one at the end of the chin.
아래 점은 턱의 아래쪽, 위 점은 턱의 끝부분에 놓습니다.
Something like this.
이런 식으로요.
Then the mouth.
그다음 입입니다.
I may want to show the textures here.
여기서는 텍스처를 표시하는 것이 좋겠습니다.
And then I can press L to select the whole mouth marker.
그런 다음 L을 눌러 입 마커 전체를 선택할 수 있습니다.
And I can move it with G.
G로 이동할 수 있고,
I can also scale it.
크기 조절도 가능합니다.
And then I'm going to scale it down a little bit.
조금 축소하겠습니다.
And then scale and press Z to scale it on the Z axis.
그리고 Scale 후 Z를 눌러 Z축으로만 스케일링합니다.
And then place these corners at the corners of the mouth.
그런 다음 모서리 점들을 입 모서리에 맞춥니다.
So you can place these dots on the outline of the mouth.
이 점들을 입 외곽선 위에 놓아도 되고,
But there is an official video from the creator of Autoreg Pro.
하지만 AutoRig Pro 제작자의 공식 영상에서는,
And he places these markers a little bit inside the volume of the mouth.
이 마커들을 입 볼륨의 약간 안쪽에 배치하더군요.
The nose.
코입니다.
This is the tip of the nose.
여기가 코끝이고,
And this is basically the top of the nose.
여기가 코의 윗부분입니다.
When aligning the eyes, I may actually want to go to object mode here.
눈을 맞출 때는 여기서 오브젝트 모드로 가는 것이 좋겠습니다.
Object mode.
오브젝트 모드로요.
And select the eyelashes.
그리고 속눈썹을 선택합니다.
When you go into the face setup, Autoreg Pro unhides all of the meshes for some reason.
얼굴 세팅으로 들어가면 AutoRig Pro가 이유는 모르겠지만 모든 메시를 다시 표시합니다.
So I'm going to hide these again.
그래서 이들을 다시 숨기겠습니다.
Select the markers again.
마커도 다시 선택하고,
Go to edit mode.
에디트 모드로 들어갑니다.
And then again go to front view.
그리고 다시 정면 보기로 갑니다.
With L, I'm going to select this whole marker for the eye.
L 키로 눈 마커 전체를 선택하겠습니다.
Press S and Z to squash it.
S를 누른 뒤 Z를 눌러 세로 방향으로 눌러줍니다.
Move it over the eye.
눈 위로 이동시킵니다.
I can rotate it and scale it.
회전하고 스케일 조절도 할 수 있습니다.
And that will give me almost perfect alignment in this case.
이렇게 하면 이 경우 거의 완벽하게 정렬됩니다.
But I can then grab each of the individual dots and place them where they should be.
이후에는 각 점을 하나씩 잡아 알맞은 위치에 배치할 수 있습니다.
So this is the inner corner of the eye.
여기가 눈의 안쪽 모서리이고,
And this is the outer corner.
여기가 바깥쪽 모서리입니다.
And the rest of the dots are just aligned at the outline of the eye.
나머지 점들은 눈의 외곽선을 따라 배치하면 됩니다.
Then we have the browse.
다음은 눈썹입니다.
And here the texture tells me exactly where to place the markers.
여기서는 텍스처가 마커를 정확히 어디에 둘지 알려줍니다.
If I was in a solid mode, I wouldn't be quite sure where to place them.
솔리드 모드였다면 어디에 놓아야 할지 확신하기 어려웠을 겁니다.
Another technique is to enable wireframe.
또 다른 방법은 와이어프레임을 켜는 것입니다.
And that may enable you to see where the placement should go.
그러면 배치 위치를 더 잘 볼 수 있습니다.
But yeah.
네, 그렇습니다.
But in this case, the texture will show us the exact placement.
하지만 이 경우에는 텍스처가 정확한 위치를 보여줍니다.
And now we come to this line here.
이제 이 선으로 넘어가겠습니다.
Which to me is the most mysterious and unclear of all.
개인적으로 여기 부분이 가장 애매하고 이해하기 어려웠습니다.
But again, if we look at the image from the official video.
하지만 공식 영상의 이미지를 보면,
It is placed something like this.
대략 이렇게 배치되어 있습니다.
Along the cheeks of the character.
캐릭터의 볼을 따라가는 선입니다.
And finally we have the ears.
마지막으로 귀입니다.
So just align this dot with the bottom of the ear.
이 점을 귀의 아래쪽과 맞추고,
And this one with the top of the ear.
이 점은 귀의 윗부분과 맞추세요.
And make sure that all dots are overlapping with the mesh.
모든 점이 메시에 겹쳐 있도록 배치해야 합니다.
If you have a dot like this, you will get an error when you press go.
이런 식으로 점이 벗어나 있으면, Go를 눌렀을 때 오류가 납니다.
I'm going to show you in a second.
곧바로 보여드리겠습니다.
And here we have the eyeball setup.
여기가 안구(eyeball) 설정입니다.
So here again, I'm going to go to object mode.
여기서도 다시 오브젝트 모드로 가겠습니다.
Select my eye mesh.
눈 메쉬를 선택합니다.
And you'll see that both eyes are joined into a single object.
두 눈이 하나의 오브젝트로 합쳐져 있는 것을 볼 수 있습니다.
So in this case, I want to select one eye object.
이 경우에는 한쪽 눈 오브젝트를 선택해야 합니다.
One.
한쪽만요.
And it will be my eyes object.
그 오브젝트가 'Eyes' 오브젝트가 됩니다.
If, if I go to edit mode.
만약 편집 모드로 가서,
And I select one of the eyes.
한쪽 눈을 선택해서
And separate it into a separate mesh.
별도의 메쉬로 분리한다면,
Then I have to select two eyes.
그러면 두 눈을 선택해야 하고,
And select the right eyeball in this field here.
여기 필드에서 오른쪽 안구를 지정해야 합니다.
But I'm going to undo.
하지만 저는 되돌리겠습니다.
Okay.
좋아요.
My eyes are again joined into a single object.
눈이 다시 하나의 오브젝트로 합쳐졌습니다.
Now I'm going to select one eyeball.
이제 안구 하나와
And my eyes object.
'Eyes' 오브젝트를 함께 선택합니다.
If this field is empty.
이 필드가 비어 있는 상태에서
And you press go.
Go를 누르면,
You'll get an error.
오류가 발생합니다.
So make sure that you enter the eyes in here.
그러니 여기 눈 오브젝트를 반드시 지정하세요.
And also here is the other error that you can get.
또 다른 오류 사례도 있습니다.
If I just move this marker outside of the mesh.
이 마커를 메쉬 바깥으로 옮기면,
And press go.
Go를 누르면,
I'll get another error.
또 다른 오류가 발생합니다.
So I'll undo.
그래서 되돌리겠습니다.
Everything is overlapping.
이제 모든 점이 메시에 겹쳐 있습니다.
Eyes are set up.
눈이 설정되었습니다.
And then I can press go.
이제 Go를 눌러도 됩니다.
And here just like in the previous example.
그리고 이전 예제와 마찬가지로,
Autoreg Pro created the bones for us.
AutoRig Pro가 뼈들을 생성해 주었습니다.
In this case.
이번에는
It also created reference bones.
참조 뼈들도 함께 생성되었습니다.
For the eyes.
눈용 참조 뼈,
Mouth.
입,
So for the whole face.
즉 얼굴 전체를 위한 참조 뼈입니다.
So usually the first thing that you should check.
보통 가장 먼저 확인해야 할 것은
Is the fingers.
손가락입니다.
And in this case.
이번 경우에는
Autoreg Pro did an almost perfect job.
AutoRig Pro가 거의 완벽하게 처리했습니다.
At detecting the fingers.
손가락을 감지하는 데요.
If some of the fingers are misaligned.
손가락 일부가 어긋나 있다면
Like this.
이런 식으로요.
In my opinion.
제 생각에는
The best way to align them.
정렬하는 가장 좋은 방법은
Is to switch to volume snapping.
볼륨 스내핑으로 전환하는 것입니다.
Keep snapping off.
스내핑은 끈 상태로 유지하고
And then move the joint.
그런 다음 관절을 이동시키고
And hold control.
Ctrl을 누른 채
And it will snap into the volume of the finger.
손가락 볼륨 안쪽으로 스냅됩니다.
Something important about the fingers.
손가락에서 중요한 점은
Is that.
바로
There is a little bit of a curvature to them.
약간의 곡률이 있다는 것입니다.
If the curvature is opposite.
곡률 방향이 반대로 되어 있으면
Like this.
이런 식으로요.
Then the rotation of the finger.
그러면 손가락의 회전 방향도
Will also be wrong.
잘못되게 됩니다.
So.
그래서
Give them the correct curvature.
올바른 곡률을 주어야 합니다.
Other than that.
그 외에는
It looks good.
괜찮아 보입니다.
Maybe the shoulder can be a little bit deeper.
어깨는 메쉬 안쪽으로 조금 더 깊게 넣는 게 좋겠습니다.
Into the mesh.
네, 메쉬 안쪽으로요.
And the elbow.
그리고 팔꿈치는,
This mesh.
이 메쉬에는
Doesn't really have a well defined elbow.
팔꿈치가 뚜렷하게 보이지 않지만
But somewhere around here.
대략 이쯤이면
Is fine.
무난합니다.
I guess.
그런 것 같습니다.
It can be a little bit hard to tell.
얼굴 참조 뼈들이
If the reference bones.
완벽한지 여부는
For the face.
판단하기가
Are perfect.
다소 어려울 수 있습니다.
But usually.
하지만 보통은
Autoreg Pro does a good job.
AutoRig Pro가 잘 해줍니다.
And here is why.
그리고 그 이유가 여기 있습니다.
We hit the eyelashes.
속눈썹을 숨겼고,
And the hair.
머리카락도 숨겼기 때문입니다.
You'll see that.
보시면,
The hair.
머리카락이
Is overlapping.
눈썹과 겹칩니다.
With the.
그래서
Brows.
만약 머리카락을
So.
선택해 둔 상태였다면,
If we had the hair.
머리카락을
Selected.
선택해 두었다면,
These.
눈썹 뼈들이
Brow bones.
머리카락
Would be.
위에
On top of the hair.
생성됐을 겁니다.
Which is.
그건 우리가
Not what we want.
원하는 바가 아닙니다.
And same with the eyes.
눈도 마찬가지입니다.
If the eyelashes.
속눈썹이
Were.
보이는
There.
상태였다면,
Then the eye bones.
눈 관련 뼈들이
Would be generated.
속눈썹 위에
On top of the eyelashes.
생성되었을 것이고,
Rather than.
실제 눈꺼풀
On the actual eyelids.
위가 아니라 그 위에 생겼을 겁니다.
So.
그래서
We helped.
우리가
Autoreg Pro.
AutoRig Pro가
Align everything.
모든 것을
Correctly.
정확히 정렬하도록
And that way.
도와준 것입니다.
We won't have to do.
이렇게 하면
Any manual.
수동 작업을
Work.
거의 안 하거나,
Or at least.
적어도
Not too much.
많이 하지 않아도 됩니다.
So.
그러니
Check your rig.
리그를 다시 확인하시고,
Again.
필요하다면
You may need.
조금 더
To align.
정렬해 주세요.
These little bones.
이 작은 뼈들은
Again.
다시,
At the edges.
발의 가장자리에
Of the foot.
맞춰 두세요.
And this one.
그리고 이건
In the middle.
가운데입니다.
So.
그래서
From here.
여기서
I can go.
이동해서
To the Autoreg Pro.
AutoRig Pro
Tab.
탭으로 갑니다.
And again.
그리고 다시
In here.
여기에서
I can select.
선택할 수 있습니다.
Any of the.
리그의
Rig parts.
어느 부분이든요.
And.
그리고
Check the limb.
각 팔다리
Options.
옵션을 확인할 수 있습니다.
Again.
이 부분은
This is something.
다음에
That we'll.
따로
Talk about.
설명할
In another video.
주제입니다.
For now.
지금은
Let's just use.
기본 설정만
The default settings.
사용해 보겠습니다.
And see.
그리고
If we can get.
좋은 결과가
Good results.
나오는지 보죠.
So.
자,
Click the magic button.
마법 같은 버튼을 클릭하고,
Match the rig.
'Match to Rig'를 실행합니다.
And get the pretty shapes.
그러면 예쁜 컨트롤 형태들을 얻습니다.
Nice.
좋습니다.
Next.
다음으로
Again.
다시
We want to skin.
스키닝을 진행하겠습니다.
The character.
캐릭터에요.
And to do so.
그렇게 하려면,
I'm going to go.
다음으로 이동합니다.
To object mode.
오브젝트 모드로 가서
Select all meshes.
모든 메쉬를 선택하고,
And then.
그리고
Shift select.
Shift로
The rig.
리그를 추가 선택합니다.
So.
그러니
Make sure.
반드시
That the rig.
리그가
Is.
활성 오브젝트
The active object.
인지 확인하세요.
Then go.
그다음
To skin.
Skin으로 갑니다.
If.
만약
If a mesh.
메쉬가
Is the active object.
활성 오브젝트라면
Then.
그때는
We won't be able.
Bind를
To click bind.
누를 수 없습니다.
So.
그래서
I'll make.
제가
The rig.
리그를
Active.
활성으로 만들겠습니다.
So.
그리고
Next.
다음으로
We already.
우리는 이미
Did this.
이걸 했고,
In the.
앞선
Simple example.
간단한 예제에서 했죠.
But the more.
하지만
The character.
캐릭터가
Gets.
복잡해질수록
The more.
더
Difficult.
어려워지고,
It is.
그만큼
To weight it.
웨이팅을
Nicely.
깔끔하게 하기 어렵습니다.
Binding.
바인딩은
Is.
리깅에서
The creation.
Armature 제작만큼이나
Of this.
중요합니다.
And that's.
그래서
Why.
AutoRig Pro가
That auto rig.
바인딩 과정을
To make.
조금
The binding.
더
Process.
쉽게
A little bit.
만들어 준다는 점이
Easier.
정말 좋습니다.
So.
이제
Let's look.
설정을
At the settings.
살펴보죠.
First.
먼저,
We have.
엔진이 있고,
And by default.
기본값은
It is set.
히트맵
To heat maps.
엔진입니다.
So.
그래서
If you have.
리깅을
A little bit.
조금이라도
Of experience.
해보셨다면,
With.
Blender의
In blender.
아마
Automatic weights.
자동 가중치 기능을 아실 겁니다.
If I have.
메쉬와
A rig.
리그를
Selected.
선택한 다음
And press.
Ctrl
Control.
+ P를 누르면,
I can choose.
다음 옵션을
With.
선택할 수 있습니다:
Automatic weights.
자동 가중치(Automatic Weights).
And that will.
그러면
Automatically.
자동으로
Assign weights.
가중치가 할당되어
To the character.
캐릭터가 바인딩됩니다.
When it works.
잘 작동할 때는
It is.
정말
Really great.
좋습니다.
The problem.
문제는
Is that.
가끔
Sometimes.
실패한다는 겁니다.
So.
그래서
Here.
여기
Autoreg Pro.
AutoRig Pro에서는
Is using.
정확히 같은
Same.
기능(자동 가중치)을
Feature.
사용하지만,
That we have.
Blender의
Automatic weights.
자동 가중치 기반입니다.
But.
하지만
It can do.
몇 가지
Some.
도움이 되는
Operations.
작업을
To help.
추가로 수행해
Avoid errors.
오류를
For example.
피하도록 돕습니다.
By default.
예를 들어,
It splits.
기본적으로
The meshes.
메쉬를
So.
분리합니다.
Very often.
그래서
The error.
자동 가중치에서 흔한
That happens.
오류는
With.
대개
Automatic weights.
겹치는
Is.
메쉬 때문에
Because.
발생하는데,
Overlapping.
겹치는
Meshes.
메쉬 때문입니다.
Which is.
그리고 메쉬가
Very.
매우
Dense.
조밀한
With.
폴리곤으로
Polygons.
이뤄져 있다면
You can.
다음 옵션을
Use.
사용할 수 있고,
This option.
이 옵션을.
In our.
이번 작업에서는
It won't.
이 옵션이
Be.
필요 없습니다.
There are.
그리고
Some.
몇 가지
Advanced settings.
고급 설정이 있는데
That.
지금은
I won't.
건드리지 않겠습니다.
For now.
이 부분은
Address.
다른 영상에서
Them.
다룰
In another.
수 있습니다.
Video.
또한
There is.
Specials가 있고,
And.
여기에서도
Here.
다시
Again.
안구
You can.
오브젝트를
Set.
지정할
Your.
수 있으며,
Object.
그러면
And.
과정이
Automate.
자동화됩니다.
It.
됩니다.
You.
네.
an opportunity to use this later in this video preserve volume will change
이 옵션은 영상 후반부에 사용할 기회가 있을 겁니다. 'Preserve Volume'은
something in the armature modifier I'm not a big fan of this option but I'll leave
Armature 모디파이어의 설정을 바꿉니다. 개인적으로 선호하진 않지만
it on and I'll show you what it does later in the video scalefix if the
이번에는 켜 둔 채 나중에 어떤 효과인지 보여드리겠습니다. 'Scale Fix'는
binding fails you can try checking this option and binding again this may fix the
바인딩이 실패했을 때 체크하고 다시 바인딩해 볼 수 있는 옵션으로,
problem again it's a little trick that Autoreg Pro does under the hood and so
문제를 고칠 수도 있습니다. 이것도 AutoRig Pro가 내부에서 쓰는
for now I'm going to keep this default options with the default heat maps engine
작은 트릭이라고 보시면 됩니다. 그래서 지금은 기본 히트맵 엔진과
make the armature active and try to bind so after a couple of seconds the
기본 옵션을 유지한 채,
process is finished and if I go to pause mode I can try to move some of the rig
Armature를 활성으로 두고 바인딩해 보겠습니다. 몇 초 뒤
parts and let's see what happens so here you can see that the arm is moving but
완료되면, 포즈 모드로 가서 리그 일부를 움직여
here there is a little part that is disconnecting this is a common problem
무슨 일이 일어나는지 확인할 수 있습니다. 여기서는 팔이 움직이지만
with heat maps but overall it is not too bad it is working and let's check the leg
이 작은 부분이 분리되는 걸 볼 수 있습니다. 히트맵에서 흔한
as well so it's also working but here I can see that the foot is stretching for
문제지만, 크게 나쁘진 않습니다. 다리도
some reason the shoe actually this is not a very common problem but for some
확인해 보면 잘 작동하긴 하는데, 발(신발)이 이유 없이
reason we are getting it here the body looks okay the head can also move well it
늘어나는 문제가 보입니다. 흔한 문제는 아니지만 여기서는
seems to be affecting part of the jacket which I don't want but we can fix this
발생하네요. 바디와 머리는 괜찮습니다. 다만 머리가 재킷의
later this is the jaw widget if I press G to move it it will open the mouth and it
일부에 영향을 주는 것 같고, 그건 원치 않습니다. 이건
actually works quite well but you can see that the teeth that are inside are
나중에 고치겠습니다. 이 컨트롤이 턱 위젯인데, G로
being deformed so this is a very common problem with Autoreg Pro
이동하면 입이 열립니다. 동작은 꽤 괜찮지만,
I'm going to show you how to fix it a bit later in the video this is the eyes
안쪽의 치아가 변형되는 걸 볼 수 있습니다. AutoRig Pro에서
widget if I disable overlays and move it around you'll see that the eyes are moving
꽤 흔한 문제라서, 영상 후반에 고치는 방법을
and we even have a little bit of eyelid deformation going on so not too bad so I
보여드리겠습니다. 이건 눈 컨트롤이고, 오버레이를 끄고
can select all bones and press Alt-R Alt-G Alt-S and that will just reset the
움직여 보면 눈이 움직입니다. 그리고 눈꺼풀 변형도
pose of the character so let's try to switch the binding engine and bind again
약간 따라옵니다. 나쁘지 않죠. 모든 뼈를 선택해
and see if we get better results so I'm going to switch to the voxelized engine
Alt+R, Alt+G, Alt+S로 포즈를 리셋하겠습니다. 그리고
and again select all meshes and have the rig as active so the voxelized engine is a
이번에는 바인딩 엔진을 바꿔 다시 바인딩해서
native feature of Autoreg Pro and it has type 1 and type 2 I usually just use type 1
더 나은 결과가 나오는지 보겠습니다. 'Voxelized' 엔진으로
there is a voxel resolution if you increase it you may get better results but the
바꾸고, 다시 모든 메쉬를 선택한 뒤 리그를 활성으로 둡니다.
process may take longer so again with the default settings let's just press bind and
Voxelized 엔진은 AutoRig Pro의 고유 기능이고 타입 1, 타입 2가 있는데
see what happens so again after 20 to 30 seconds the process is finished and I can
보통 저는 타입 1만 사용합니다. 'Voxel Resolution'을 높이면
go to pose mode and try to move the arm and here you'll notice right away that
더 좋은 결과를 얻을 수 있지만 시간이 더 걸릴 수 있습니다. 그러니
this little piece that was disconnecting before is no longer disconnecting and
이번에도 기본 설정으로 'Bind'를 눌러 보겠습니다. 20~30초 후
overall this engine will give you better results with overlapping geometry so again
작업이 완료되면 포즈 모드로 가서 팔을 움직여 보세요. 아까
let's try to move the leg and see what happens and the shoe is actually fine now
다리를 움직여 보면서 어떤지 확인해 보죠. 신발은 이제 괜찮습니다.
if I rotate the leg around there is just a little bit of clipping between the skin
다리를 회전해 보면 피부와
and cloth here we can fix it manually or you can try to play around with the
의복 사이에 약간의 클리핑이 있습니다. 수동으로 고치거나
voxelized settings the head will also move fine you'll see that the jacket is no
Voxelized 설정을 조정해 볼 수 있습니다. 머리도 잘 움직이고, 재킷은 더 이상
longer affected but there is a little bit of a problem with the skin here down here
영향을 받지 않습니다. 다만 아래쪽 피부가 조금 문제가 있습니다.
again this is not too much of a problem
그래도 큰 문제는 아닙니다.
but now we come to the disadvantages of voxelized skinning if I try to open the
하지만 이제 Voxelized 스키닝의 단점으로 넘어가 보면, 입을
mouth you'll see that it doesn't open at all basically voxel skinning is great at
열려고 해도 전혀 열리지 않습니다. 기본적으로 Voxel 스키닝은 겹치는
overlapping geometry but when there is polygons that are just close to each
지오메트리에는 강하지만, 서로 아주 가까운 폴리곤들은
other then they'll get fused together like this and also the eyes actually they
이런 식으로 서로 붙어버리게 됩니다. 눈도
they're kind of okay but overall heat maps gave us better results for the face and
그럭저럭 괜찮지만, 전체적으로 얼굴은 히트맵이 더 좋고
voxelized gave us better results for the body and there is one more option voxel
바디는 Voxelized가 더 좋은 결과를 줍니다. 그리고 또 하나의 옵션,
heat diffuse skinning add-on so if you click on it you may see this message saying
Voxel Heat Diffuse Skinning 애드온이 있습니다. 클릭하면
that the add-on is not installed I actually have this add-on and I made a
애드온이 설치되어 있지 않다는 메시지가 나올 수 있습니다. 저는 이 애드온을 갖고 있고
video about it so if I go to edit preferences add-ons and look for voxel heat
관련 영상을 만들어 둔 상태입니다. Edit > Preferences > Add-ons에서 'Voxel Heat
diffused skinning and just enable the add-on as soon as it is enabled the
Diffuse Skinning'을 찾아 활성화하면,
warning message will disappear and AutoRig Pro will let me use this add-on
경고 메시지가 사라지고 AutoRig Pro에서 이 애드온을 사용할 수 있게 됩니다.
but instead of going to the official tab of the add-on I can use it from here so
그리고 애드온의 공식 탭으로 가지 않고도, 여기에서 바로 사용할 수 있습니다.
just for fun let's try to bind with this add-on and it's finished now if we try to
시험 삼아 이 애드온으로 바인딩을 해 보겠습니다. 완료되었고,
pose the character you may find a slight differences the overlapping of the sleeves
캐릭터를 포즈해 보면 약간의 차이가 보일 겁니다. 소매의 겹침이
is a little bit better and in the foot if I rotate it around you'll see that skin
조금 더 좋아졌고, 발을 회전해 보면
and cloth are not clipping at all and here if I rotate the head you'll see that the
피부와 의복이 전혀 클리핑되지 않습니다. 그리고 머리를 회전하면
problem with the skin that we had is gone there is a little bit of problem with the
아까 피부에서 보이던 문제가 사라진 걸 볼 수 있습니다. 다만 이제는
cloth now so there is no perfect solution but you see that this add-on has some
의복 쪽에 약간의 문제가 생깁니다. 완벽한 해법은 없지만,
advantages so if you're okay with spending some additional money you can
이 애드온이 장점이 있다는 것은 분명합니다. 약간의 비용 지출이 괜찮다면
also buy this add-on it's really great I use it a lot and again I have a
이 애드온을 구매해도 좋습니다. 정말 훌륭해서 저는 자주 사용하고,
dedicated video about the add-on itself but the native voxelized engine works
애드온 자체만 다룬 전용 영상도 있습니다. 물론 기본 제공 Voxelized 엔진도
great as well so you can use that so I'm going to bind with voxelized again
아주 잘 작동하니 그걸 사용하셔도 됩니다. 이제 다시 Voxelized로
actually let's try type 2 just so we don't rely on any paid add-ons okay so
바인딩하겠습니다. 이번에는 유료 애드온에 의존하지 않도록 'Type 2'를 써 보죠.
it's done let's see the results really quickly hmm actually the actually the
완료되었습니다. 결과를 빠르게 확인해 보죠. 음, 실제로
clipping here is fixed that is nice oh and the clipping in this area is fixed as
여기 클리핑이 고쳐졌네요. 좋습니다. 그리고 이쪽 영역의 클리핑도
well so it's definitely worth playing around with these binding settings but
수정되었습니다. 그러니 이 바인딩 설정들을 만져 보는 것이 확실히 가치가 있습니다.
of course with a voxelized engine you'll always get this problem in the face so if
물론 Voxelized 엔진을 쓰면 얼굴에서의 문제는 늘 따라옵니다. 따라서
I just select the face go to edit mode and press alt a to deselect everything and
얼굴만 선택해 편집 모드로 들어가 Alt+A로 전부 해제한 다음,
press L while hovering over the face that will select all face vertices then I can go
얼굴 위에서 L을 눌러 얼굴 버텍스를 모두 선택합니다. 그런 다음
to object mode and shift select the armature let's go to pause mode and really
오브젝트 모드로 돌아가 Armature를 Shift로 추가 선택합니다. 포즈 모드로 가서
quickly select everything alt R alt G alt S
빠르게 모두 선택하고 Alt+R, Alt+G, Alt+S로 초기화합니다.
and next in object mode I'm going to switch back to heat maps and choose
다음으로 오브젝트 모드에서 히트맵으로 다시 전환하고,
selected vertices only and then bind so now my face is weighted with heat maps so the
'Selected Vertices Only'를 선택한 뒤 바인딩합니다. 이제 얼굴은 히트맵으로
mouth will open well but for everything else the voxelized waiting will be kept so
웨이팅되므로 입은 잘 열리지만, 나머지 부위는 Voxelized 웨이팅이 유지됩니다.
I'm really loving this workflow and if this wasn't a tutorial I would just go
이 워크플로우가 정말 마음에 듭니다. 튜토리얼만 아니었다면
through these settings really quickly and it would take less than a minute okay
이 설정들을 빠르게 훑고 1분도 안 걸렸을 겁니다.
now the character is rigged and weighted so it can move with the rig but there
이제 캐릭터는 리깅과 웨이팅이 되어 리그와 함께 움직일 수 있지만,
are a couple of problem areas so I'm going to move the rig around and try to notice any problems
몇몇 문제 구간이 있습니다. 리그를 이리저리 움직이며 문제를 찾아보겠습니다.
and then we'll try to fix them actually this clipping problem is there I'm not sure why it seemed to be
그리고 고쳐 보죠. 사실 이 클리핑 문제는 여전히 있네요. 전엔 사라진 것처럼 보였는데 왜 그런지는 모르겠습니다.
gone before but for the most part the problems will be in the face you'll see that the teeth are
대부분의 문제는 얼굴에서 발생합니다. 치아가 심하게 늘어나고 있어서 반드시 고쳐야 합니다. 여기는 원래 눈을 감게 해야 하는데,
stretching really badly so I'll definitely fix this this here is supposed to close the eye but
웨이트가 썩 좋지 않습니다. 조금 손봐야겠고, 이 문제도 함께 다뤄 보겠습니다.
the weights are really not good so I'll work on it a little bit and maybe we'll try to address this
여기 문제도요. 요컨대 대부분은 웨이트 페인팅 문제입니다. 그 전에 간단히
problem here so it's mostly weight painting problems and by the way let me quickly address
'Preserve Volume' 옵션을 짚고 넘어가겠습니다.
this preserve volume option so we always had this setting checked while binding the mesh what this does
우리는 메쉬를 바인딩할 때 이 설정을 항상 켜 두었습니다. 이게 하는 일은,
is yeah I'll just raise the oops I'll just raise the leg a little bit now go to object mode select
일단 다리를 조금 들어 올린 다음(어… 실수), 오브젝트 모드로 가서
the mesh go to the modifier tab and here is the armature modifier which connects the mesh to the bones
메시를 선택하고 모디파이어 탭으로 가면, 뼈와 메쉬를 연결하는 Armature 모디파이어가 있습니다.
and in here you'll see this preserve volume option by default blender doesn't use it but I guess the
여기에서 'Preserve Volume' 옵션을 볼 수 있습니다. Blender 기본값은 꺼짐이지만,
developer of Autoreg Pro likes it so this Autoreg Pro setting here automatically enables this
AutoRig Pro 개발자는 이 옵션을 선호하는 듯합니다. 그래서 ARP의 해당 설정이
setting in the armature modifier I don't like this setting because it tends to bulge out some areas
Armature 모디파이어의 이 옵션을 자동으로 켭니다. 저는 이 옵션을 그리 좋아하지 않습니다. 특정 부위가 볼록해지는 경향이 있고,
of the rig and also it doesn't transfer to game engines so it may make your character's deformation
게임 엔진으로는 이 설정이 전달되지 않기 때문입니다.
better in blender but this will be lost if you export out of blender if you only plan to animate
즉 Blender 내부에서는 변형이 좋아 보일 수 있지만, Blender 밖으로 내보내면 이 이점이 사라집니다.
inside blender then you can have it on or off whatever looks better to you I'm going to turn it off but if
오로지 Blender에서만 애니메이션할 계획이라면 켜거나 꺼서 더 좋아 보이는 쪽을 선택하세요. 저는 끄겠습니다. 그리고
you plan to export the character then definitely turn it off okay now let's start fixing the problem areas
캐릭터를 내보낼 계획이라면 반드시 끄는 것을 권합니다. 이제 문제 구간을 고치기 시작하겠습니다.
I'll hide the main body mesh and focus on the teeth so again I have upper teeth lower teeth and
메인 바디 메쉬를 숨기고 치아에 집중하겠습니다. 윗니, 아랫니, 혀 오브젝트가 있고,
a tongue object I'll select the upper teeth and before we fix the weights we want to make sure that
윗니를 선택하겠습니다. 웨이트를 고치기 전에, 치아와 혀에 해당하는 뼈가 올바른 위치에 있는지 확인해야 합니다.
the bones that correspond to the teeth and tongue are positioned correctly so I'll go back to the rig tab
그래서 리그 탭으로 돌아가
select the rig and click edit reference bones and that will give me again the reference bones or the
리그를 선택하고 'Edit Reference Bones'를 클릭합니다. 그러면 다시 레퍼런스 본, 즉 메타리그가 나타납니다.
meta rig whatever you want to call it and you'll find the teeth bones above and below the tongue bones
혀 뼈 위아래로 치아 뼈들을 찾을 수 있습니다.
so these three bones are the tongue bones this is the central teeth bone and this is the right
이 세 개가 혀 뼈이고, 이것이 중앙 치아 뼈, 이쪽이 오른쪽
teeth bone and this is the left upper teeth bone why do we have left and right actually you don't need
치아 뼈, 그리고 이쪽이 왼쪽 윗니 뼈입니다. 왜 좌우가 있냐고요? 꼭 모두 사용할 필요는 없습니다.
to use all of them that will just allow you to bend the teeth which may be useful in cartoony characters
치아를 구부리게 만들어 카툰 스타일에서 유용하게 쓰려는 용도입니다.
so I'm going to select the jaw bone because it is very large and it makes it hard to see what
턱 뼈가 아주 커서 작업이 잘 안 보이니 턱 뼈를 선택해 H로 숨기겠습니다. 그리고 윗니의 세 뼈를 모두 선택해
I'm doing so selected press H and then I'll select all of these three upper teeth bones go to the side
측면 뷰로 가서 윗니의 볼륨 안쪽에 배치합니다.
view and place them inside the volume of the upper teeth and then from the front view I'll place the
그다음 정면 뷰에서 윗니의 양쪽에 뼈를 배치합니다.
bones on the sides of the teeth of the upper teeth same thing for the lower teeth just select these three
아랫니도 동일하게, 이 세 뼈(Teeth Bottom Ref)를 선택해
bones they're called teeth bottom ref from the side view place them around here from the front
측면에서는 이쯤에, 정면에서는 약간 옆으로 옮겨 두면 됩니다. 이제 오브젝트 모드에서
view move them a little bit to the side and that will be it and now in object mode i'm going to
둘 다 선택하고(윗니/아랫니) 두 치아 오브젝트를 숨긴 다음, 리그로 돌아가 에디트 모드로 갑니다.
and move the tongue bone and move the tongue bones into position something like this so you can edit
그리고 혀 뼈를 적절한 위치로 옮깁니다. 이런 식으로요. 이렇게 레퍼런스 본은 리그 생성 후에도,
these reference bones even after you generate the rig once and even after binding the character to
그리고 캐릭터를 리그에 바인딩한 뒤에도 수정할 수 있습니다.
the rig this is not so much thanks to autoreg pro but thanks to blender blender is very flexible in
이는 AutoRig Pro 덕분이라기보단 Blender의 유연성 덕분입니다.
this regard so even at this point if i find that the shoulder is not rotating correctly i can just
즉, 이 시점에서도 어깨 회전이 올바르지 않다면 관절을 잡아 움직여 재배치해,
grab this joint and move it around reposition it and basically change the point of rotation of the
사실상 회전 축을 바꿔 줄 수 있습니다. 매우 강력하고, Blender가 이런 걸 허용해 주는 것이 정말 멋집니다.
shoulder that can be very powerful it's very cool that blender can do that so when i'm done editing
레퍼런스 본 편집을 마치면, 혹시 모르니 Alt+H로 숨긴 뼈를 모두 다시 보이게 하고,
the reference bones just in case i'm going to press alt h to unhide any hidden bones this is good
'Match to Rig'를 다시 실행합니다. 이제 치아와 혀 위젯이
practice and match the rig again now you'll see that these teeth widgets and the tongue widgets are
정확한 위치에 배치된 것을 볼 수 있습니다. 다음으로 오브젝트 모드에서 Alt+H로 모두 보이게 하고,
placed exactly where they should be so next i'll go to object mode alt h to unhide everything and then
메인 메쉬를 숨겨 치아가 잘 보이도록 한 뒤, 이 윗니 메쉬를 선택해
i'll hide the main mesh so that i can see the teeth again and so i'll select this upper teeth mesh go to
데이터 프로퍼티의 Vertex Groups에서 'Delete All Groups'를 눌러 모두 삭제합니다.
the data properties and here on the vertex groups i'll just click here and choose delete all groups
즉, 이 캐릭터에 적용돼 있던 모든 웨이트가 제거됩니다. 아랫니에도 동일하게 적용하고,
so any weighting that we had on this character will be gone let's do the same for the lower teeth
혀에도 적용합니다. 이제 리그 포즈 모드에서 턱 위젯을 움직여 보면,
and for the tongue so now if i go to the rig pose mode and move this jaw widget you'll see that it no
치아와 혀가 더 이상 함께 움직이지 않는 것을 볼 수 있습니다. AutoRig Pro에서 수동으로 웨이트를 조정할 때
longer moves the teeth and the tongue when manually tweaking the weights in autoreg pro it is important to
중요한 점은 변형(Deformation) 본들이 마지막 레이어에 있다는 것입니다. 일부는 여전히 뼈가 아니라
know that the deformation bones are here on the last layer you'll see that some of them still look like
도형처럼 보일 수 있는데, Viewport Display에서 Shapes를 끄면 바꿀 수는 있습니다. 하지만
shapes not like bones you can kind of change this if you go to viewport display and disable shapes but
중요한 건, 마지막 레이어에 있는 것들은 모두 변형 본이라는 점입니다. 레이어 1과
it doesn't matter everything that is here on the last layer is deformation bone and on layer one and
2에는 컨트롤이 있습니다. 웨이트 작업을 할 때는 마지막 레이어로 가고, 나머지 레이어에 있는 것들은
two are the controls so when you want to work on weights go to the last layer and all other layers
이른바 메커니즘 본으로, 리그의 자동화를 만들어 줍니다. 건드리지 않는 게 좋습니다.
These are so-called mechanism bones, they create the automations in the rig, and it's
건드리지 않는 게 좋습니다.
So now, to weight the teeth, I'm going to use again some of the advanced skinning options.
이제 치아를 웨이팅하기 위해, 고급 스키닝 옵션을 다시 사용하겠습니다.
So I'm going to select the three teeth bones, right, center, left and right, and then go
치아 뼈 세 개(오른쪽, 중앙, 왼쪽)를 선택하고,
to skinning, and disable selected vertices only, and enable selected bones only.
Skinning에서 'Selected Vertices Only'는 끄고, 'Selected Bones Only'는 켭니다.
So now, because I have these three bones selected, AutoRig Pro will only use them for weighting.
이제 이 세 개의 뼈만 선택돼 있으므로, AutoRig Pro는 웨이팅에 이 뼈들만 사용합니다.
I'll go to object mode, select the upper teeth, shift-select the rig, I'll choose voxelized,
오브젝트 모드로 가서 윗니를 선택하고, 리그를 Shift로 추가 선택한 다음, 'Voxelized'를 선택하고
and again make sure that I have this setting enabled, and click bind.
해당 설정이 켜져 있는지 다시 확인한 뒤, 'Bind'를 클릭합니다.
Now if I go to pose mode, and move the bones, nothing seems to happen, so I guess it failed.
이제 포즈 모드에서 뼈들을 움직여 봐도 변화가 없네요. 실패한 것 같습니다.
Let's try to use heatmaps then, same settings, and click bind.
그럼 히트맵으로 시도해 보죠. 같은 설정으로 'Bind'를 클릭합니다.
Now it's only, now it's only assigned to this bone, hum.
이번엔 이 한 뼈에만 할당됐네요, 음.
Oh, okay, I didn't have all bones selected, I just had to select all bones, and then with
아, 모든 뼈를 선택하지 않았군요. 모든 뼈를 선택한 뒤 히트맵으로
heatmaps, click bind, and now you see that each bone kinda deforms the upper teeth.
Bind를 누르면, 이제 각 뼈가 윗니를 적절히 변형시키는 걸 볼 수 있습니다.
And don't worry, if we enable the controls, here's this main control that moves the whole
걱정 마세요. 컨트롤을 켜면, 윗니 전체를 움직이는 메인 컨트롤이 있습니다.
upper teeth.
윗니 전체를요.
And most of the time you won't even move these controls, you'll just open the jaw, and then
대부분은 이런 세부 컨트롤을 직접 움직일 필요가 없습니다. 턱을 열면
everything will move automatically.
나머지는 자동으로 함께 움직입니다.
Let's keep binding, and you'll see how it works.
바인딩을 계속하면서 작동 방식을 보여드리겠습니다.
So select the lower teeth, shift-select the armature, enable only the last layer, go to
아랫니를 선택하고, Armature를 Shift로 추가 선택한 뒤, 마지막 레이어만 표시하고
pose mode, select the three teeth bones, and with these same settings, click bind.
포즈 모드에서 치아 뼈 세 개를 선택해 같은 설정으로 Bind를 누릅니다.
Okay.
좋습니다.
Now if I enable the main controls, and open the jaw, the teeth will move with the jaw.
이제 메인 컨트롤을 켜고 턱을 열어 보면, 치아가 턱과 함께 움직입니다.
And here I can kinda deform the teeth.
여기서는 치아를 변형시킬 수도 있고,
Or move the whole thing.
전체를 움직일 수도 있습니다.
And now we only need to take care of the tongue, which we'll do in the same way, just undo.
이제 혀만 처리하면 됩니다. 같은 방식으로 진행하겠습니다. 방금 작업은 되돌리고요.
Okay, I'll hide the teeth.
좋아요, 치아는 숨기겠습니다.
Select the tongue, shift-select the rig, pose mode, enable the deform bones, hold shift while
혀를 선택하고, 리그를 Shift로 추가 선택한 뒤 포즈 모드에서 변형 본을 보이게 하고,
selecting all of these three tongue bones, and with the same settings, click bind.
Shift를 누른 채 혀 뼈 세 개를 모두 선택해 같은 설정으로 Bind를 누릅니다.
Okay.
좋습니다.
Now in object mode, I can unhide everything.
이제 오브젝트 모드에서 전부 다시 보이게 할 수 있습니다.
Select the rig, and enable the control bones, or control shapes.
리그를 선택하고 컨트롤 본(컨트롤 셰이프)을 보이게 하세요.
Go to pose mode, and if I grab the jaw and move it, you'll see that it opens the mouth.
포즈 모드에서 턱을 잡아 움직이면 입이 열리는 것을 볼 수 있습니다.
The teeth and tongue are also moving properly with the jaw.
치아와 혀도 턱과 함께 올바르게 움직입니다.
If you wanna move the tongue, you can do it like this.
혀를 움직이고 싶다면 이렇게 하시면 됩니다.
You can rotate these controls, you can also move them and stretch them, if that helps you
이 컨트롤들을 회전할 수도 있고, 필요하다면 이동·늘려서 원하는 변형을
achieve the deformation that you want.
얻을 수 있습니다.
And that's it.
이 정도면 됩니다.
The mouth and jaw should be fixed now.
이제 입과 턱은 정리되었습니다.
Now let's focus on the eye.
이제 눈에 집중해 보겠습니다.
So it seems like the upper lid is deforming the lower lid, which is not good.
윗눈꺼풀이 아랫눈꺼풀까지 변형시키고 있는 것 같습니다. 바람직하지 않습니다.
And also it has too much influence over the polygons above the eye.
또한 눈 위쪽 폴리곤에 영향이 지나치게 큽니다.
So here we're going to be doing good old-fashioned weight painting, and I have a full playlist
여기서는 전통적인 방식의 웨이트 페인팅을 하겠습니다. 기초를 배우고 싶다면
about weight painting if you wanna learn the basics.
웨이트 페인팅 재생목록을 참고하세요.
Here I'm going to go a little bit fast, but I'm going to tell you the most important stuff.
여기서는 조금 빠르게 진행하되, 가장 중요한 포인트는 말씀드리겠습니다.
So go to object mode, and I'm going to hide the lashes again, the eyelashes.
오브젝트 모드로 가서 속눈썹을 다시 숨기겠습니다.
Select the rig, and again unhide the deformation bones, and then shift-select the mesh, and
리그를 선택해 변형 본을 다시 보이게 하고, 메시를 Shift로 추가 선택한 다음
go to weight paint mode.
웨이트 페인트 모드로 갑니다.
Right?
좋죠?
And you may want to click on the x-ray button here, so that you don't see the bones through
여기 X-Ray 버튼을 눌러 뼈가 메쉬를 관통해 보이지 않게 할 수도 있습니다.
the mesh.
메쉬를 통해서요.
And now if I control-click, and now if I control-click on this bone, I should see what it affects,
이제 컨트롤+클릭으로 이 뼈를 선택하면, 어떤 부분에 영향을 주는지 보여야 하는데
but it looks like I have the hair selected, rather than the face.
지금은 얼굴이 아니라 머리카락이 선택돼 있는 것 같습니다.
So let's select the rig, shift-select the face, and then go to weight paint mode.
그래서 리그를 선택하고, 얼굴을 Shift로 추가 선택한 다음 웨이트 페인트 모드로 갑니다.
And if I control-click here, I'll see what parts of the mesh are affected by this shape.
이제 여기서 컨트롤+클릭하면, 이 셰이프가 메쉬의 어느 부분에 영향을 주는지 볼 수 있습니다.
And it may not be super obvious, but you'll see that there is a little influence on the
아주 눈에 띄지는 않지만, 아랫눈꺼풀에 약간의 영향이 있는 것을 볼 수 있습니다.
lower lid.
아랫눈꺼풀에요.
So let's go to tool, where you'll find the options for weight painting.
이제 Tool 패널로 가면 웨이트 페인팅 옵션이 있습니다.
And here, under symmetry, I want to enable mirror vertex groups, and also the x option.
Symmetry에서 'Mirror Vertex Groups'와 X 축 미러를 켭니다.
So that way, anything that I do on this side of the mesh will be mirrored on the other side,
이렇게 하면 한쪽에서 한 작업이 반대쪽에도 반영되어, 양쪽을 따로
and I don't have to manually paint both sides.
페인팅할 필요가 없습니다.
Next under option, I'm going to enable auto-normalize.
Option에서 'Auto-Normalize'도 켜겠습니다.
I always enable this option, and that saves me some trouble.
저는 항상 이 옵션을 켭니다. 여러 문제를 예방해 줍니다.
Please refer to the weight painting playlist if you want an in-depth explanation.
자세한 설명은 웨이트 페인팅 재생목록을 참고해 주세요.
But for now, I'll set weight to zero, which means that I'll be removing weights here.
여기서는 Weight를 0으로 두겠습니다. 즉, 이 영역의 웨이트를 제거하겠다는 뜻입니다.
The strength I can keep to one, and with F, I'm going to make my brush a little bit bigger,
Strength는 1로 두고, F로 브러시 크기를 조금 키운 뒤
and paint on the lower lid, and make sure that all of the light blue color disappears.
아랫눈꺼풀을 칠해, 옅은 파란색이 완전히 사라지도록 하겠습니다.
You can also enable show zero weights.
'Show Zero Weights'를 켤 수도 있습니다.
And that will allow you to easily see weights that are greater than zero.
그러면 0보다 큰 웨이트를 쉽게 식별할 수 있습니다.
So for some reason, the mix mode didn't quite remove the weights fully.
가끔 믹스 모드만으로는 웨이트가 완전히 지워지지 않습니다.
So I'll switch to subtract mode, and set the weight to one.
그래서 Subtract 모드로 전환하고, Weight를 1로 설정하겠습니다.
So I'm fully subtracting the weights, and then click until the whole lower lid becomes black.
웨이트를 완전히 빼내는 것이죠. 아랫눈꺼풀이 완전히 검정(0)으로 될 때까지 클릭합니다.
And then also ctrl-click on the next shape, and do the same.
그 다음 이 인접한 셰이프도 Ctrl+클릭해 같은 작업을 합니다.
I want to remove all influence of this bone below the upper lid.
윗눈꺼풀 아래 영역에서 이 뼈의 영향력을 모두 제거하고 싶습니다.
Okay, this also affects a little bit too much of this, of the cheek.
그리고 볼(뺨)쪽에도 영향이 과합니다.
So paint it out, similarly here.
여기도 칠해서 제거합니다. 이쪽도 비슷하게요.
Let's see the angle, and I'll keep erasing the weights.
각도를 바꿔 보면서, 웨이트를 계속 지워 나가겠습니다.
Okay, let's see the bones on the lower lid.
이제 아랫눈꺼풀의 뼈들을 보겠습니다.
So again, I don't want them to affect the upper lid at all.
역시 윗눈꺼풀에는 전혀 영향을 주지 않도록 하겠습니다.
And also, I'm going to erase the weights that go too far down.
그리고 너무 아래쪽까지 내려간 웨이트도 지우겠습니다.
Okay, something like this.
좋아요, 이런 느낌으로요.
And then again, I'll go through the bones on the upper lid.
이제 다시 윗눈꺼풀의 뼈들을 훑겠습니다.
And I'm going to reduce the strength of the subtraction, and I want to remove the influence
Subtract의 강도를 낮춰서, 이 뼈가 눈썹 위쪽에 주는 영향은
of this bone over the brow, basically.
없애 주겠습니다.
Okay, same with this bone.
이 뼈도 마찬가지입니다.
Reduce the strength, and try to erase the weights, so that it only affects this part of
강도를 낮추고, 눈꺼풀의 이 부분에만 영향을 주도록 웨이트를 지웁니다.
the upper lid.
윗눈꺼풀의 일부만요.
Okay, so I think this may be starting to work now.
좋습니다. 이제 슬슬 제대로 작동하기 시작한 것 같습니다.
So let's go to object mode, select the rig, unhide the controls, go to pause mode, and
오브젝트 모드로 가서 리그를 선택하고, 컨트롤을 보이게 한 뒤 포즈 모드에서
try to close the eye.
눈을 감아 보겠습니다.
And you'll see that it's much better.
훨씬 좋아졌습니다.
It doesn't affect the lower lid.
아랫눈꺼풀에는 영향을 주지 않습니다.
But it looks like the central bone is affecting the sides too much.
다만 중앙 뼈가 양옆에 영향을 조금 과하게 주는 것 같습니다.
So let's close the eye, shift select the mesh, and go to weight paint mode again.
그래서 눈을 감은 상태에서 메시를 Shift로 추가 선택하고, 다시 웨이트 페인트로 갑니다.
Control click on this central bone.
이 중앙 뼈를 Ctrl+클릭합니다.
And I'm still in subtract mode.
지금은 여전히 Subtract 모드입니다.
So I'll try to subtract some of these weights from the sides.
그래서 양옆에서 웨이트를 조금 빼내 보겠습니다.
And also subtract the weights that the edge of the eye has on these eyelids.
그리고 눈 가장자리(엣지)가 눈꺼풀에 주는 영향도 일부 빼내겠습니다.
And now I'll switch back to mix, and with these same settings, weight to 1 and strength
이제 다시 Mix로 전환하고, Weight는 1, Strength는 낮게 둔 채
to something low, I'm going to try to click in this area to make these vertices more affected
이 영역을 클릭해, 이 뼈의 영향이 조금 더 커지도록 하겠습니다.
by this bone.
이 뼈의 영향이요.
So it's almost there, I just don't really like the outer edge of the eye.
거의 다 됐습니다. 다만 바깥쪽 눈가(외측 엣지)가 마음에 들지 않네요.
So again, select the rig, shift select the mesh, weight paint mode, and I guess this bone
그래서 리그를 선택하고, 메시를 Shift로 추가 선택해 웨이트 페인트로 가서,
shouldn't be affecting the upper lid that much.
이 뼈가 윗눈꺼풀에 그 정도로 영향을 주진 않도록 하겠습니다.
So let's go back to subtract mode, and subtract these weights.
다시 Subtract 모드로 전환해 웨이트를 빼냅니다.
Also it goes too far into the temples.
관자놀이 쪽으로 너무 멀리 영향이 가네요.
So now I can control click on this control and try to close the eye again.
이 컨트롤을 Ctrl+클릭하고, 다시 눈을 감아 보겠습니다.
Let's try to paint some weights for this central bone over here on the side of the lid.
이번에는 중앙 뼈의 웨이트를 눈꺼풀 옆면(사이드)에 조금 칠해 보겠습니다.
So mix mode, low strength, and I'll paint just a little bit.
Mix 모드, 낮은 강도로 아주 조금만 칠합니다.
Okay, so the solution was actually to paint some weights for the edge of the eye on the
결국 해결책은, 눈 가장자리의 웨이트를 눈꺼풀 옆면에 약간 칠하는 것이었습니다.
side of the eyelid.
옆면에요.
You can keep painting the weights, this process can be very time consuming, but you can get
오브젝트 모드로 돌아오면, 이제 눈이 제법 자연스럽게 감깁니다.
even better results.
웨이트를 계속 칠해 나가면
Another tool that you can use is the blur tool.
더 좋은 결과를 얻을 수 있지만, 시간이 꽤 걸릴 수 있습니다.
And I'm going to call this one done for now.
또 다른 도구로 블러(Blur) 도구도 사용할 수 있습니다.
So another problem area that you may encounter are the eyelashes.
지금은 이 정도로 마무리하겠습니다.
I'm going to press Alt H to unhide them.
또 하나 마주칠 수 있는 문제 구간은 속눈썹입니다.
Here they are.
Alt+H로 속눈썹을 보이게 하겠습니다.
And now if I close, you'll see that they don't really follow the eyelids.
여기에 있네요.
So here is a very powerful technique that you can use, not only for eyelashes, but
이제 눈을 감아 보면, 속눈썹이 눈꺼풀을 제대로 따라가지 않는 걸 볼 겁니다.
it will help in this case.
속눈썹뿐 아니라 여러 경우에 유용한
I'm going to delete all groups for these eyelashes.
아주 강력한 기법을 보여드리겠습니다. 이 경우에도 도움이 됩니다.
I want to set the weights anew, and I'll go to the modifiers and add a data transfer modifier.
우선 이 속눈썹의 모든 그룹을 삭제합니다.
I'll move it above the armature modifier.
웨이트를 새로 설정하려고 합니다. 모디파이어에 가서 'Data Transfer' 모디파이어를 추가합니다.
And then as a source, I'm going to use the picker and choose the body or the face mesh.
그리고 Armature 모디파이어 위로 이동시킵니다.
Then I'm going to enable vertex data, and in the options, vertex groups.
그 다음 소스로는 피커를 사용해 바디(또는 얼굴) 메쉬를 선택합니다.
And then press the generate data layers button.
그리고 Vertex Data를 켜고, 옵션에서 'Vertex Groups'를 선택합니다.
So now if I go back to the data properties, you'll see that we have the vertex groups again.
'Generate Data Layers' 버튼을 누릅니다. 그러면 데이터 프로퍼티로 돌아갔을 때
But now if I go to my rig and go to pose mode and move the eyelid a little bit, you'll see
이제 리그로 돌아가 포즈 모드에서 눈꺼풀을 조금 움직여 보면,
that now the eyelash is trying to move with the eyelid, but not quite.
속눈썹이 눈꺼풀을 따라가려 하긴 하지만 완전히는 아닙니다.
So that is because this modifier is live.
그 이유는 이 모디파이어가 라이브 상태이기 때문입니다.
So as I'm moving the control, this modifier is being updated.
컨트롤을 움직일 때마다 모디파이어가 갱신되죠.
To avoid that, I want to apply the modifier.
이를 피하려면, 모디파이어를 적용해야 합니다.
So click this triangle and choose apply.
여기 삼각형을 눌러 'Apply'를 선택합니다.
Now if I go to the rig and move the eyelid, you'll see that the behavior is different.
이제 리그에서 눈꺼풀을 움직여 보면 거동이 달라진 것을 볼 수 있습니다.
It's still not perfect.
여전히 완벽하진 않습니다.
That is because the transfer didn't quite propagate to the end of the eyelid.
전달이 눈꺼풀의 끝부분까지 충분히 퍼지지 않았기 때문입니다.
I'm going to enable bioframe.
와이어프레임을 켜 보겠습니다.
So the eyelash mesh is kind of big.
속눈썹 메쉬가 꽤 큽니다.
Here is its end actually, over here.
끝부분이 사실 여기까지 와 있네요.
And so now we're going to have to do a little bit of additional weight painting.
그래서 약간의 추가 웨이트 페인팅이 필요합니다.
So select the rig, shift select the eyelash.
리그를 선택하고, 속눈썹을 Shift로 추가 선택합니다.
And actually, I'll go to edit mode and press L, and then L one more time on the other side
그리고 편집 모드로 가서 L을 누르고, 반대쪽도 한 번 더 L을 눌러 윗속눈썹을 선택합니다.
to select the upper eyelashes.
P를 눌러 별도의 오브젝트로 분리합니다.
So this is again the power of Blender.
이것이 Blender의 장점입니다.
It allows us to separate and join objects, and the weights just stay together.
오브젝트를 분리/결합해도 웨이트는 그대로 유지됩니다.
By separating these meshes, I don't have to worry that I'll be painting on the lower
메쉬를 나누면 아랫속눈썹을 실수로 칠할 걱정 없이,
eyelash, and I can just focus on the upper one.
윗속눈썹에만 집중할 수 있습니다.
So select the rig, shift select the eyelash, weight paint mode, and now I'm going to control
리그를 선택하고, 속눈썹을 Shift로 추가 선택한 뒤 웨이트 페인트 모드로 가서,
click on this here, which is the control of the upper eyelid.
여기 윗눈꺼풀 컨트롤을 Ctrl+클릭합니다.
And I can try to blur, I guess, a little bit.
조금 블러로 퍼뜨려 볼 수도 있겠지만,
But yeah, I'll have to paint.
결국은 직접 칠해야 합니다.
So blend mix, weight to 1, and strength to something low.
Blend는 Mix, Weight는 1, Strength는 낮게 설정합니다.
And I'm going to paint at the top of the eyelash.
속눈썹의 윗부분을 칠하겠습니다.
Okay, then select this control here, and paint some weights, and this control, and paint some
그다음 이 컨트롤을 선택해 웨이트를 조금 칠하고, 이 컨트롤에도
weights over here.
약간 칠하겠습니다.
And then maybe the edge, and paint some weights, and then I'll blur a little bit, but not too
가장자리에도 조금 칠하고, 살짝 블러로 부드럽게 하되 너무 심하진 않게 합니다.
much.
과하지 않게요.
So I guess I have to paint a little bit more here at the top.
윗부분을 조금 더 칠해 줘야 할 것 같습니다.
Okay, and now we're getting something that is working.
좋아요, 이제 어느 정도 원하는 동작이 나옵니다.
I can both go back to the rig and test the behavior.
리그로 돌아가 거동을 테스트할 수 있습니다.
And yeah, I can work with that.
네, 이 정도면 사용 가능합니다.
With more painting, it can get even better.
더 칠하면 더 좋아질 겁니다.
It just takes time.
시간이 조금 들 뿐이죠.
So take your time with the weight painting.
웨이트 페인팅은 천천히 시간을 들여 하세요.
And in the end, maybe, let's maybe fix this problem here.
마지막으로, 여기 문제도 고쳐 보겠습니다.
So just create this pose where the problem is visible.
문제가 잘 보이도록 그 포즈를 먼저 만들어 두세요.
Go to object mode, shift select the mesh, go to weight paint mode, and control click
오브젝트 모드로 가서 메시를 Shift로 추가 선택하고, 웨이트 페인트 모드로 간 뒤
on a deforming bone.
변형 본을 Ctrl+클릭합니다.
So if I enable x-ray here, I can see the bones better.
여기서 X-Ray를 켜면 뼈가 더 잘 보입니다.
I want to select the lower leg bone.
아래다리(하퇴) 뼈를 선택하겠습니다.
And then if I disable overlays, and just use the blur brush and blur a little bit,
그다음 Overlays를 끄고 블러 브러시로 살짝만 블러링해도,
you'll see that we basically fix the problem with just a little bit of blurring.
조금의 블러만으로 사실상 문제가 해결됩니다.
And if we move around, we may find additional problems.
다른 포즈로 움직여 보면 추가 문제를 발견할 수도 있습니다.
And you can keep blurring or try a little bit of painting, and it should become perfect.
그땐 계속 블러로 다듬거나 약간 칠해 주면, 결국 깔끔해질 겁니다.
So I hope you enjoyed this full workflow with AutoRig Pro.
이번 AutoRig Pro 전체 워크플로우가 도움이 되었기를 바랍니다.
We did spend some time on fixing weight painting issues.
웨이트 페인팅 문제를 고치는 데 시간을 꽤 썼죠.
This is very normal, AutoRig Pro does help a lot, but some manual work is unavoidable.
이건 아주 정상입니다. AutoRig Pro가 많은 도움을 주지만, 어느 정도 수작업은 피할 수 없습니다.
And I wanted to make sure that you'll have all of the necessary tools to rig your first character
여러분이 첫 캐릭터를 리깅하는 데 필요한 모든 도구를 갖추셨으면 해서
with AutoRig Pro.
이 내용을 준비했습니다.